<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
>
<channel>

  <title>Travel Blog: John and Amanda&#39;s EuroTrip</title>
  <description></description>
  <!--<pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2017 19:11:40 </pubDate>-->
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jun 2012 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
  <language>en-US</language>
  <wp:wxr_version>1.2</wp:wxr_version>

  <wp:author>
    <wp:author_id></wp:author_id>
    <wp:author_login><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></wp:author_login>
    <wp:author_email><![CDATA[ jbwilhite@gmail.com ]]></wp:author_email>
    <wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[ John Wilhite ]]></wp:author_display_name>
    <wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[ John ]]></wp:author_first_name>
    <wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[ Wilhite ]]></wp:author_last_name>
  </wp:author>

 

  <item>
    <title>Welcome</title>
    <pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2012 18:22:57 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1337119115</guid>
    <description>Clemson, SC</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-05-15 18:22:57</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-05-15 22:22:57</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Welcome</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Welcome<br/>Clemson, SC </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Clemson, SC</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
Hi there,<br> Thanks for reading our blog! I am John Wilhite and my wife Amanda and I are about to embark on a six week backpacking tour of of Europe. Our plan is to travel cheap and experience as much authentic Europe as we can. We will be hitting the must see cities and also getting plenty of small town and local flavor, all while (hopefully) avoiding the tourist traps. Stay tuned for more entries as we go, but right now it's all about packing.<br> <br> Because were on a tight budget, we're traveling the European way: Camping. We will probably stay in some hostels, but camping is the cheapest (and most interesting) way to see the continent. In the US, we think of camping as rustic settings far from cities, but pretty much all towns and cities in Europe have one or more campsites. They have many facilities including showers, laundry, bars, restaurants, bike rentals etc. Most are easily accessible by public transportation, which is great for us because we will be train hopping the whole trip.<br> <br> For our trip, we are traveling as lightly as possible. We are carrying camping gear that most hostel backpackers wouldn't need, so we have to go light on everything else. We are splitting the tent between our packs, but we each have our own sleeping pad and Thermarest Sleep System. We both have 50 liter Osprey backpacks.<br>  <br> My packing list includes:<br> Tent Body, Poles, Stakes<br> 2 Long Sleeve and 2 Short Sleeve Shirts<br> 1 Pair of Pants<br> 1 Pair of Shorts<br> 3 Pairs of Underwear and Socks<br> Tanktop and Shorts as Pajamas<br> Rain Jacket<br> Packable Daypack<br> Toiletries and Camp Towel<br> Money Belt<br> Backpack Rain Cover<br> Teva Walking Shoes<br> Vibram FiveFingers for camp/shower shoes<br> Travel Cup and Utensil<br> Phone and Charger<br> Camelbak<br> <br> Amanda is packing:<br> Tent Footprint and Rainfly<br> 1 Long Sleeve and 2 Short Sleeve Shirts<br> 2 Tanktops<br> 1 Dress<br> 1 Pair Convertible Pants<br> 1 Pair Capri Pants<br> 2 Scarves<br> 3 Pairs of Underwear and 2 Bras<br> 1 Pair of Socks (Her shoes are made to be worn w/o socks)<br> Toiletries and Camp Towel<br> Laundry Detergent and Clothesline<br> First Aid Kit<br> Travel Purse<br> Money Belt<br> Backpack Rain Cover<br> Jambu Walking Shoes<br> Chaco Flip Flops<br> Travel Cup and Utensil<br> Phone and Charger<br> Camera, Charger, Extra Battery and Extra Memory Card<br> Camelbak<br> <br> <br> <br> <br> <br> <br> 
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Itinerary</title>
    <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2012 17:46:09 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1337291138</guid>
    <description>Clemson, SC</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-05-17 17:46:09</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-05-17 21:46:09</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Itinerary</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Itinerary<br/>Clemson, SC </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Clemson, SC</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
Our Plan (Subject to Change):<br> <br> June 8 Fly out of Charlotte<br> 3 Days London<br> 3 Days Paris<br> 3 Days Belgium<br> 2 Days Amsterdam<br> 3 Days Copenhagen<br> 2 Days Prague<br> 2 Days Vienna<br> 2 Days Hallstatt<br> 2 Days Salzburg<br> 2 Days Munich<br> 1 Day Innsbruck<br> 4 Days Jungfrau Region of Switzerland<br> 2 Days Zermatt<br> 3 Days Lake Como<br> 4 Days Cinque Terre<br> 2 Days Florence<br> 2 Days Orvieto<br> 3 Days Rome<br> July 24 Fly out of Rome<br> <br> <br> Detailed Itinerary<br> <br> <br> 
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>It&#39;s Aliiiiive!!!</title>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2012 09:17:38 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1338988658</guid>
    <description>Anderson, SC</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-06-06 09:17:38</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-06 13:17:38</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>It&#39;s Aliiiiive!!!</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> It&#x27;s Aliiiiive!!!<br/>Anderson, SC </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Anderson, SC</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
Excerpt from The Birth of Frankenguide<br> <br> "On a tepid moonlit night in May, in the far reaches of Oconee county, a mostly sane scientist began preparing his laboratory for his newest creation. One he had been planning for minutes, possibly even an hour. He took a brand new and unsuspecting guidebook, and he began to hack out the sections that he fancied. The gleaming blade of his XACTO knife cut through the pages like they were paper. He added parts from other guides and bound them together until the creation barely resembled its former self. Only after he had applied his own embellishment, the creator was able to marvel at his own ingenuity."<br> <br> <br> Guidebooks are great but for any trip, but when ounces and pack space are at a premium, carrying a full size Lonely Planet Western Europe guidebook can be a hassle. This is a situation where a kindle would be great (for downtime reading too), but since we don't have one, we have to make do. So I took our guidebook and cut out the pages I thought we might need. I easily omitted hundreds of pages (and ounces!) just for Greece and Spain and only kept the London, Paris, and Munich sections of the UK, France and Germany respectively. <br> <br> I also printed out travel sections for Copenhagen and Prague from wiki travel since those cities weren't included. I added few pages from online articles about various hiking trails, directions to campsites, and whatever else I found to be interesting.<br> <br> I punched holes in the pages and bound the book with some card stock and zip ties. Then I used some creative license to make a stencil and spray paint a fitting "Frankenguide" design on the outside.
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>We&#39;re Off!</title>
    <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2012 16:01:41 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1339185701</guid>
    <description>Charlotte, NC</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-06-08 16:01:41</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-08 20:01:41</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>We&#39;re Off!</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> We&#x27;re Off!<br/>Charlotte, NC </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Charlotte, NC</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
After months of planning, it's finally time to leave. Right now, Amanda and I are killing a couple hours at the airport bar in Charlotte. We are both really excited, it hasn't seemed real until we actually got to the airport. I've been flying around the world for years, so I'm a good bit less nervous than Amanda. This is her first time out of the country, and only her second ever plane trip. It's commendable that that she has committed to a trip like this on her first ever time overseas. She is a trooper, and I know we will have a great time. The time change might be a little rough because we will land at 7am GMT in London, which will be like trying to wake up at 2am EST. It shouldn't be much of a problem for Amanda. After working night shift for 3 years, she's used to running on little to no sleep. We really appreciate all the well wishes we have gotten, and we look forward to updating everyone along the way!
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>London</title>
    <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1339417839</guid>
    <description>London, United Kingdom</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-06-11 00:00:00</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-11 04:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>London</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> London<br/>London, United Kingdom </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>London, United Kingdom</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
First Step: London Well our plane was delayed 2 hours so we didn't make it to London until 9am.&#160; We landed at London Gatwick which is about an hour south of the city.&#160; While Gatwick is a bit more out of the way than Heathrow, Charlotte runs direct flights daily to Gatwick, so we saved a good bit of time and headaches by avoiding transfers.&#160; We made it to our hostel about 1pm GMT and had to wait an hour or so to check in.&#160; We splurged a bit staying here, but in London (the most expensive city on our trip) even the cheap hostels are not very cheap.&#160; Our hostel is an old house and has a good bit of character. It even has a restaurant and bar downstairs. Even though we were tired from the flight and we lost some time from the delay, we managed to get out and walk Hyde Park and Piccadilly Square on our first day.&#160; Unfortunately Buckingham Palace was closed for repairs.&#160; On day two, we hit the famous landmarks: Tower of London, Tower Bridge, South Bank of the Thames, Parliament, Big Ben, Westminster Abbey, Harrod's and Soho.&#160; We also went to King's Cross Train Station to get a picture of the famous 9 3/4 platform sign.&#160; Amanda's sister Ellen is the biggest Harry Potter fan, and she would've killed us if we didn't get a picture for her.&#160; We had been surviving on deli sandwiches, fruit and nuts until we went to have real fish and chips last night.&#160; It has been raining all day today, and we have to catch the train to Paris at 5:30pm, but we went out to Wembley to see England's national stadium this morning.&#160; Before we go to the train station, we are going to try to get up to see Emirates Stadium, home of Arsenal. Click here to see more pictures!
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Paris</title>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2012 06:26:44 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1339669604</guid>
    <description>Paris,  France</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-06-14 06:26:44</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-14 10:26:44</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Paris</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Paris<br/>Paris,  France </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Paris,  France</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
Paris was our first camping spot. The campground was nice, but the weather was cold and rainy. Luckily our one season sleeping bags and complimentary airline blankets were warm enough. Paris itself was the same as when I was here 8 years ago: grand, historic, long lines and dirty. Maybe we were holding too high of standards because we had just come from London, where they are cleaning and updating for the Olympics. Mme. Parris would be glad to know that I can still speak a little French. I could ask some simple questions, but if the answer was too long or spoken to quickly, then I was lost. Luckily only a couple of people didn't speak English, and I could still get my point across. The first night we arrived, we just caught the last bus to the campground and had to set up the tent in the dark. The first full day we walked a good chunk of the city, from the Arc de Triomphe to the Louvre, past Notre Dame to the Latin Quarter. The highlight of Amanda's trip so far was walking around the Sephora store on the Champs-&#201;lys&#233;es. Day two we saw the Eiffel Tower and its mile long lines, and the great panoramic views from Montmartre. It had seemed like a nice day that morning, so we washed our clothes and hung them up to dry, but it poured rain as soon as we got on the shuttle back to the campground. We had to pay &#8364;4 just to dry our clothes in the machine. The international crowd at the campground was very interesting. It seemed mostly like families and older couples, but there was a van of Australian girls near us who seemed like they were on a European party tour. Our last night we had fun drinking wine and watching the Germany vs Netherlands soccer match with a bunch of Germans and Dutch people. I think we were the only neutrals in the campground bar. When we were using one the campground computers (Internet is a precious commodity here, probably more so than public restrooms), we overheard an Italian family's discussion on how to google search for KFCs in Paris (we saw several). The youngest son's contribution was to repeatedly yell "Kentucky! Kentucky!". Now we're off to Belgium to escape the madness of the megacities. Hopefully even as we go north, it will warm up some (maybe the time difference here is 6 months and not 6 hours?).
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Belgium</title>
    <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2012 07:38:53 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1339760333</guid>
    <description>Brugge,  Belgium</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-06-15 07:38:53</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-15 11:38:53</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Belgium</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Belgium<br/>Brugge,  Belgium </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Brugge,  Belgium</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
Belgium: the land of Beer, Chocolate, Waffles, and Fries. London is roughly the size of New York, Paris is close to Chicago, Bruges (Brugge in Dutch) is similar in size and feel to Charleston or Savannah. The coast is a few miles away, but the historic center of Brugge is medieval buildings, cobblestone streets, and canals. But before we could get to Brugge, we had a few difficulties along the way. Our last morning in Paris, we made it to the train station fairly early. After standing in the wrong line for 20 minutes, we were directed to the correct line, which had a 1 hour wait. When we got to the counter, we were told our railpasses did not cover the train to Brussels. We would have to pay full price for the high speed train leaving in 15 minutes, or wait and get on local trains with a several convoluted transfers. The two women at the counter didn't give us much choice and were barely understandable, so we reluctantly paid the &#8364;60 for the high speed train. When we got to Brussels, we knew there were a few sights we wanted to see. Amanda and I both have a good sense of direction and don't often get lost, but we found Belgium very confusing. We had no trouble with the London Underground or the Paris Metro, but the trains, subways, and buses in Belgium gave us a great amount of difficulty. We had to search the subway station in Brussels a good fifteen minutes before we found a line map. Then we entered the stop going the wrong direction and there was no way to change directions without going completely out (and wasting our ticket). In every other city, you enter and then pick the direction. Once inside the station, we had to walk to another line just to find a map. We were able make it to the center of town in a round about manner. We made to the Grand Place because we could see the spires from our station, but we couldn't find the cafe we had picked out for lunch (the guidebook only gave an address, street signs are sometimes hard to find as well). There were probably a dozen Italian and Greek places near the square, and the only Belgian places served just beer. Since our time in Brussels was limited and we were starving, we had Greek. After wandering the square for a while, we set off to look for the beer museum. The guide book map did not show the museum, and there were only some vague directions. After a little bit of searching with no luck, we decided that we would make sure we had a good map of each city that we tackled. We returned to the train station and boarded the next train to Brugge. We saw on the departures board that the train went to Ghent first, then on to Brugge (or so we thought). We were supposed to transfer trains in Ghent, but we ended up riding several stops too far. By the time we figured out what was going on, our car was deserted, and we got off at a stop called Bissegem (we looked it up later, it's almost in France) to try to get on a train going back the opposite direction. The Bissegem station consisted of a stretch of gravel and a bench on either side of the track. We couldn't make head or tail of the posted timetables, but we were able to make some sense of them after talking to nice old lady who spoke a little bit of English. We ended up waiting about 45 minutes to ride one stop back to Kortrjik, where we could catch the train to Brugge (No maps at any of these places). At the Kortrjik station, we waited another 45 minutes for the Brugge train. While we were waiting for the train, we talked to three Canadian girls, one who now lives in Brussels, who were going the same way. We decided it would be a good idea to follow them. We finally made it to Brugge about 3 hours later than we had intended, and surprisingly got on the right bus to the campground, Camping Memling. After we checked in and set up our tent, we were pretty hungry again. We walked back towards town and found that the bus had stopped running and everything around us was closed except for a fast food place called Quick. We reluctantly decided to go in, but soon found the Quick to be an oasis in an otherwise frustrating day. Though we never go to McDonald's or Burger King at home, the Quick's greasy burger and a fountain drinks (with ice!) were a welcome relief. The Quick also had free wifi so we hung out there a little bit; we checked emails and Facebook, and I posted the Paris entry. We are hoping the campground in Amsterdam has a computer so we can upload the pictures from Amanda's camera to Facebook. So far we have only posted London pictures. The historic center of Brugge was very nice. The outside edge is surrounded by a canal and modern suburbs. The inside consists of medieval buildings and churches, the streets are all cobblestone, and there are several smaller canals that weave through the center. Brugge is fairly touristy, but it's easy to dodge the crowds by avoiding a couple streets. We started by heading into the Markt, the main square of Brugge, which is dominated by the impressive belfry tower. We decided to try the famous Belgian fries we had heard so much about. At the Friterie, we ended up striking up a conversation with a family from Florida, after we heard them trying to figure out what was so special about the fries. They were plain fries, and the only interesting part was the array of sauces, ranging from gravy to curry ketchup. The oldest son is at FSU, and understandably not a Clemson fan. The most interesting place in Brugge was De Halve Maan brewery. We went on a tour that was capped off by some of the brewery's excellent internationally award winning beer. They had versions ranging from 6% to 11% alcohol (Patrick you would love this place). We also visited a bar that claimed to be the oldest in Brugge. The owners were documented all the way back to 1515. Inside we had some more beers from other parts of Belgium and talked to an older couple from Washington State and a local Belgian man named Jan. Jan has been coming to the bar for 40 years. He showed us a very old book written about the bar; it was kept outside, so it wasn't in great shape. We sampled the big 4 of Belgium: beer, chocolate, waffles, and fries. The only real disappointment was the fries. They weren't anything you couldn't get at the Bantam Chef. We decided that Brugge is our favorite stop so far, but we are really looking forward to Amsterdam.
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Amsterdam</title>
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2012 07:01:58 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1340103718</guid>
    <description>Amsterdam,  Netherlands</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-06-19 07:01:58</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-19 11:01:58</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Amsterdam</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Amsterdam<br/>Amsterdam,  Netherlands </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Amsterdam,  Netherlands</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
Amsterdam was the next stop on our list, and at 750,000 people or so, it is a fairly large city, but still more manageable than London and Paris. Amsterdam is famous for its liberal attitude towards drugs and prostitution, and even a walk through the Red Light District at 2 in the afternoon can be interesting. One thing you quickly learn in Amsterdam, a cafe is a bar/restaurant, but a coffee shop is where marijuana is sold. There is probably a coffee shop on every block. We left early from Brugge, because we were worried we might have another train fiasco like last time, but everything went well. We have started picking up a little Dutch, but the words we know almost much exclusively apply to transportation. We have taken enough trains and trams to learn that: volgende halte = next stop, bestemming = ending, Maandag = Monday, Vridag = Friday, Zaterdag = Saturday, Zondag = Sunday (We have no idea what the other days of the week are, all the timetables list Maandag-Vridag times). Many Dutch words sound similar to the English counterparts, even if the spelling if significantly different. Maybe that is why everyone in Amsterdam spoke perfect English. Often they would just start out speaking English to us and wouldn't bother with the Dutch. We arrived at the campground earlier than we were used to, and decided to just hang out at the campground restaurant/bar for the evening. The place started to fill up because of the Euro soccer tournament: Netherlands was playing Portugal, and Germany was playing Denmark. Pretty soon the place was packed with German and Dutch supporters. Netherlands ended up losing 2-1 to Portugal, an eliminating third loss for a team projected to be one of the favorites. The Dutch take their voetball very seriously, and were not at all pleased with their team's poor showing. Since Netherlands was eliminated, the next day we saw workers in the city pulling down the giant inflatable soccer balls and orange streamers that lined the streets. Our campground was more like what I expected from our European camping experience. There were virtually no tents in Paris, and Brugge was nice but very quiet. There was a much younger and rowdier vibe to Amsterdam, which is as attributable to the city as anything else. The campground didn't seem to have quiet hours and somewhat catered to those who were enjoying Amsterdam's "liberties". While the other campgrounds were mostly camper vans and families, Camping Zeeburg was young people and tents. We were directed to set up anywhere in a large field full of tents. Plus there were goats and chickens and donkeys... no idea why. The city of Amsterdam is fairly walkable, but we made use of the convenient tram system. The roads are set up so that there are two wide lanes for trams and buses, two narrow lanes outside that for cars, and outer narrow bike and scooter lanes. The car lanes were the least used; seems like everyone, young or old, rides a bike in Amsterdam. There several canals that circle the center of Amsterdam, and there are dozens of bridges over the canals. On every one of these bridges, there are dozens of bicycles chained or propped up. At first we thought they belonged to the people in the area, but we felt a few of the tires and figured out that they were abandoned. I guess when you get a new bike in Amsterdam, you just leave the old one wherever it happened to be. Amsterdam is a very relaxed place, and we spent a good bit of our time just sitting at cafes and watching the people walk/bike by. It seems like all the cafes are full around 3 in the afternoon with locals having a few beers (does anyone work here?). So we joined in, had a beer, and laughed at the bicycles narrowly dodging the tourists (we like to think we blend in a little bit better: we don't wear fanny packs, tie our jackets around our waist, or wear shirts that say "Amsterdam"). One of the more interesting foods we tried was Dutch Croquettes, or bitterballen. They are some sort of beef and gravy that is breaded and fried. I'm not sure exactly what was in them, but they were good! We also stopped a a lunch counter place and had a couple Dutch sandwiches. I had half sliced liver and half salted beef, and Amanda had smoked eel, both were very different but delicious. Though I'm a little ashamed to admit it, I was "hit" by a bike, but it was more like a graze. Funny thing though, it was in the campground and on the sidewalk, so I don't think I deserve any blame. A couple was renting bikes and getting the rundown on how to use them in the city, but they apparently weren't instructed on how to brake. These were fixed gear bikes with pedal brakes. After the girl bumped into me, the guy nearly ran into the back of her. So hopefully they learned how to brake before any real damage was done. Overall we really enjoyed Amsterdam. We had a lot of fun just enjoying the laid-back atmosphere of the city. I'm sure there's great deal more experiences to be had in Amsterdam, but I guess we will have to come back! Next up, night train to Copenhagen!
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Copenhagen</title>
    <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1340191607</guid>
    <description>Copenhagen, Denmark</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-06-20 00:00:00</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-20 04:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Copenhagen</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Copenhagen<br/>Copenhagen, Denmark </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Copenhagen, Denmark</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
Copenhagen is a city of contrasts: it is a historic city with some of the most modern buildings in the world, it is a major metropolitan area with a small city feel and it is a utilitarian port with artistic flair. Copenhagen has a population of over one million people, but the city center is so tight and organized, you would never know it. We thought we saw a lot of bikes in Amsterdam, but the people in Copenhagen live on their bikes. I read somewhere that 70% of the citizens ride a bike daily, but it seems like more. The increase of bikes and decrease of cars make the city center feel less congested and more enjoyable. With some apprehension, we reserved our beds in a 6 bed couchette on the night train to Copenhagen on our first day in Amsterdam. On the day of departure, we got lucky. We arrived at the station an hour early, and while waiting at the platform, we were told the train departure had been moved to Utrecht (30 minutes southeast). If we had not been early, we might not have made the train. We knew our cabin would be tiny, but it was still surprisingly small (the pictures don't do it justice). We were hoping that the transfer to Utrecht meant we might have less people in the cabin, but the other four people made it too. We got lucky with our bunk mates; there was a young Swiss couple, a young Australian guy, and a middle aged Australian lady (the two Aussies didn't know each other). The Swiss couple spoke perfect English, so we all talked for a few hours before sleeping. Everyone was nice, and they didn't seem like they would rummage through our stuff in the middle of the night. We spent a good bit of time with them watching Holland and Germany go by in the hallway outside our cabin. I guess nobody wanted to spend the entire 15 hours cooped up in a bunk that we couldn't even sit up in. When we got to Copenhagen, we took a regional train straight to our campground (this campground was the furthest from a city center yet - about 7km). The walk from the station to the campground took us through a park with a big historical house and the Aquarium of Denmark. The campground was situated in the middle of a beach park that got very crowded during the day. The area was a destination in itself, and we spent the rest of the day exploring the surrounding beach and parks. The campground was, by far, the nicest and most interesting so far (and the most expensive). The camping area was set up inside a former fort that protected Copenhagen's harbor from 1887 to 1934. The bunkers and cannons were still there. One of the bunkers was converted to the kitchen/lounge/bathrooms area, but was designed in an industrial modern way. The Danish are big on architecture and interior design, and we saw countless nice buildings and spaces. Ironically we were camping in a fort, but it was the least secure place we have been to yet. It seems like many people figured out that the shortest way to the beach was through the campground, so there was a lot of foot traffic by our tent during the day. But everything was fine. I talked to a few of the people, and the Danes seem very friendly. One thing we have noticed in Europe is increased efforts towards energy conservation. Utility costs are much higher over here and it shows. Most lights, especially in the bathrooms, are on a motion sensor. Some sinks in the US have the knobs you have to push down for the water to run, then cut off after 15 seconds or so. Here, the showers are either like that, or require coins for water. Either way, it annoys you into speeding up the process. In all honesty, the weather so far has been not been great. Every city has been colder than usual, but it seems like it clears up right after we leave. There has been a cold and rainy patch of weather moving at about our same speed and direction. So it was surprising that we had some sun when we arrived in Copenhagen. But it didn't last; the bad weather caught back up with us on our last day here, and it poured. Next up is Prague, a good ways south, so we should finally escape this stubborn weather system. Though I'm sure we will miss it when we are sweating in Italy.
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Relatively Speaking</title>
    <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1340401127</guid>
    <description>Copenhagen, Denmark</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-06-22 00:00:00</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-22 04:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Relatively Speaking</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Relatively Speaking<br/>Copenhagen, Denmark </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Copenhagen, Denmark</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
I always like to try to better understand things by comparing them to something familiar. After we got started, I was trying to visualize how far we were really going, and I found this map. I picked US cities and places that are roughly similar to our European itinerary. It is amazing how small Europe really is (or how big the US is). I thought it was interesting, so I decided to share it: London - Milwaukee Paris - Louisville Brugge - Cleveland Amsterdam - Detroit Copenhagen - Buffalo Prague - Baltimore Vienna - Wilmington Salzburg - Charlotte Switzerland - Knoxville Milan - Atlanta Florence - Jacksonville Rome - Orlando
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Our sleep setup</title>
    <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1340400314</guid>
    <description>Copenhagen, Denmark</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-06-22 00:00:00</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-22 04:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Our sleep setup</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Our sleep setup<br/>Copenhagen, Denmark </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Copenhagen, Denmark</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
During the planning phase, we spent a good deal of time figuring out our sleeping setup. At first we thought we would just take sleeping bags, but our bags were bulkier and warmer than we needed, so we explored some other options. For as many nights are we are camping, a constrictive sleeping bag would be no fun. We decided to buy Therma-rest Tec Blankets and Therma-rest fitted sheets to go on our air mattresses. The blanket is like a thin sleeping bag but it doesn't include the bottom, so it is much lighter and packs smaller. The sheet fits over the air mattress and has several snaps along the edge. The blanket snaps onto the sheet to stay in place. The sheets and blankets can also snap to each other to form a connected mattress and blanket. It had been colder than we thought so far, and we ended up buying a 2pack of fleece blankets in Belgium. So far the setup has worked really well, and it is more like sleeping in a bed than regular camping.
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Prague</title>
    <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1340445253</guid>
    <description>Prague,  Czech Republic</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-06-23 00:00:00</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-23 04:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Prague</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Prague<br/>Prague,  Czech Republic </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Prague,  Czech Republic</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
The jump from Copenhagen to Prague has to be the most drastic of any on our trip. While Copenhagen was clean, modern, efficient and expensive, Prague is expansive, historic, and a little rough around the edges. Probably the biggest difference is the residents. It wasn't uncommon to see men in Copenhagen wearing designer suits on bicycles. In Prague, it seemed like everyone picked out their outfits by being blindfolded at Goodwill. For the US equivalent, check out this website. The city of Prague is roughly the same size as Copenhagen but is more spread out and feels twice as large. Prague is also the first city we encountered any hills in since Paris, though I'm sure we will see plenty of "hills" in Austria and Switzerland. Prague is a very historic city, and remarkably well preserved considering all the wars and conflicts that have taken place in Central Europe. The city is somewhat of a bridge between Eastern and Western Europe, and the lingering effects of Communism can still be felt. In Copenhagen, when reserving our night train to Prague, we decided to get the 4 bed cabin. We got lucky because no one else booked the other two beds. We spread out, set up the table, played cards and ate dinner in comfort. When we got to Prague, we headed straight toward our hostel on the east end of town. We booked hostels in Prague and Vienna because we are only spending a couple days in each. We had been camping for almost two weeks, and sleeping indoors is a nice break. Our hostel was cleverly named the Czech Inn, and provided a much more social atmosphere than our last hostel in London. It seemed like 90% of the guests were native English speakers, mostly Americans, Canadians, Australians, and British, whereas the campgrounds are mostly mainland Europeans. Prague is also regarded as somewhat of a party city, and many of our roommates were taking advantage of the nightlife. While it might seem annoying to share a room with people coming and going at all hours, it worked surprisingly well. They left around the time we went to bed, and came back in when we were waking up. The most noticeable difference in Prague is that the dollar goes much, much further. We felt a little like the group in the movie Eurotrip, when they arrive in Eastern Europe and book a luxury hotel for a handful of change. In Copenhagen, a meal would cost around 150 Danish Kroners, and a Prague meal set us back 150 Czech Korunas. Though they sound the same, that's roughly $25 and $7.50, respectively. Not only were the meals a quarter the price, they were much heartier. It seems like Czech Republic is a meat and potatoes type country. We ate very well, and didn't have to worry about our budget. We were surprised at the first restaurant by the huge portions. We had grown accustomed to eating smaller meals throughout the day, but in Prague, it seems like every meal is a feast. At one restaurant, we thought we were ordering goulash, and at 180CZK ($9), it seemed like a good deal. But when they started bringing the food out, we realized it was a three course meal with potato soup, goulash, and gelato style ice cream for dessert. The Czech have definitely had the best food so far. The Czech Republic is well known for its beers. While not as famous or specialized as Belgium, the Czechs produce a wide variety of quality beers. Again the prices were great; We could sit down at a restaurant or beer garden and get a good pint for 25-30 CZK or $1.25 to $1.50. Needless to say, we sampled more beers here than anywhere else. I wanted to stay longer, but Amanda would be the first to tell you that she didn't like Prague initially. Coming from Denmark, it is quite a culture shock. Prague is a nice city, but it is rougher around the edges than any place we have been to so far. When we were out of the tourist districts, the sidewalks were uneven and rough, the was more graffiti, the people had worse haircuts and even worse taste in fashion. The public transport is functional, but not fancy. We bought passes, but never had to scan them or show them to anyone. The buildings are all either historic or remnants of the Communist era. I say this gives the city a different character, and Amanda agreed with me by the end of our stay. After some adjusting, she enjoyed Prague too. Prague has a surprising number of great sights and attractions to not be a mega city. We first visited the Old Town Square, which is the historic commercial nexus of the city. Now the streets that radiate out are all modern shopping streets, and it is a nice walking area. On the square is the famous Astronomical Clock. At every hour, a crowd gathers around, points their cameras upwards, and waits for the little show. We were on the square twice and managed to narrowly miss it. Our fellow hostelers informed us that we weren't missing much though. Apparently some elaborate cuckoo clock contraption pops out and winds around the clock. Prague Center is split by the Vltava river. Old Town Square is on the east bank, while Prague Castle and Lesser town are on the west bank. On our second day we explored the castle, which is supposedly the largest castle complex in the world. I believe it, because we could have probably spent all day there. Though it is less like what we think of as a castle, and more like a walled city on a hill The castle provides great panoramic views over the city, and has its own cathedral in the center. St. Vitus Cathedral is just as impressive as Notre Dame in my opinion, and the wait was 0 minutes vs Notre Dame's 2 hours (and we were there on a weekend). Below the castle and along the river is Lesser Town. Lesser town is the newer part of the city (it's only about 600 years old). There are many old shops, streets and churches here, but the most interesting sight is the Lennon Wall. Somewhat of a public memorial to John Lennon, the wall is a huge, ever-changing graffiti mural. Most of the "art" is dated, and all the dates I saw was within the past week. Prague was great, and I wish we had another day or so. We got a good feel for the city, and we will have to come back to see the rest. Next stop Vienna!
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Vienna</title>
    <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2012 03:45:04 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1340783104</guid>
    <description>Vienna,  Austria</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-06-27 03:45:04</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-27 07:45:04</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Vienna</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Vienna<br/>Vienna,  Austria </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Vienna,  Austria</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
Vienna was a little different than I expected. I thought of Vienna as somewhat of a quaint old city with the sounds of Mozart and operas ringing in the streets. While the city center is very historical, Vienna (Wien in German) is a modern bustling city. Vienna is a smaller version of London, both are historical and modern, with plenty of small parks and tree lined streets. A busy city with around 1.5 million people, Vienna is very relaxed and livable for its size. Vienna is Amanda's favorite city so far, and it is certainly up there on my list. We only had one full day here, but we felt like we saw a lot of what the city has to offer. The food was good, and still cheap compared to the rest of Europe. The city is not perfect though. The waiters are known for not being overly nice, but the people of Vienna seemed pretty friendly. The city allows smoking in restaurants and bars, which is almost extinct in the rest of Western Europe. Not only is it allowed, but pretty much everyone actually smokes in the restaurants. Both places we went to eat were very good and reasonably priced. Neither had menus in English though. Amanda and I are adventurous eaters, so we stuck to the meals of the day and rolled the dice. For lunch, she could tell she was ordering spinach, so I assumed it was a salad. Her meal ended up being some sort of pur&#233;ed spinach with hashbrowns and an egg on top. She's says its the weirdest meal she's ever eaten, but she enjoyed it. I thought was getting noodles, but it turns out that kn&#246;del is a potato dumpling. My meal was much more normal, and very delicious, stuffed pork tenderloin with potato dumplings. At dinner, we figured out that h&#252;hner is chicken and puten is turkey. Amanda had the huhnerschnitzel and I had puten natur mit champignon sauce und reis (natural turkey with mushroom sauce and rice). We decided to trash our money belts in Vienna. Amanda had been just keeping hers in her purse, because it is too difficult to get money or cards out of it in public. I lost my debit card because it's just as easy to put the card between the money belt and my pants, as it is to put the card into the money belt pocket. I'm guessing it fell out of my pants leg in Copenhagen. I had a scare in Vienna because the snap came undone, and I thought the money belt (with my passport, credit cards and cash) was missing. Luckily my shorts held it in place on the side of my leg. They were only $4 on Amazon, so I guess we got what we paid for. We will just have to be careful with our pockets and her purse. We went on a long looping walk through the center of the city, and north to Praterstern and the Danube. In town, we saw more grand old historic buildings than we can remember. Praterstern is a historical theme park sitting in a park on the northeast side of town. The ferris wheel was built in 1897 and is one of the oldest in the world. All our literature made references to an Orson Welles scene from the "famous" movie The Third Man shot here. I've never heard of this movie, so I don't see how it could be that famous. We also saw the Danube from Donauinsel (Danube Island). The island is a several kilometer long skinny artificial island built in the middle of the Danube (or maybe they expanded the river around this part of land). The island is basically one long park, and is popular with bikers and joggers. We heard that there is a nude beach on either end, but the walk was too far to investigate. Vienna is a shopping city. There are tons of pedestrian streets with all the really expensive famous stores: Louis Vuitton, Gucci, Chanel, Tiffany and so on. On one of the less expensive streets, we found a cool graphic design and screen printing shop called Motmot (Design Website and Shop Website). We had some Tshirts printed, and talked to the owner while he was printing. He is originally from California and his girlfriend is from Italy, and they met while in college in California. She convinced him to move to Vienna and they opened up the shop. He said Vienna took some getting used to, but it's a good place to live. In one of the more touristy areas, we saw the most impressive street performers we seen so far. It is difficult to explain (check out the video at the bottom), but is basically an optical illusion to make one guy look like he is floating above the other. They must have some sort of elaborate hidden platform. They must've sat there, not moving, for over an hour, because we walked by several times. We didn't have a whole lot of time for Vienna, but we really enjoyed what we did see. We still have a couple weeks in German speaking countries, so maybe we will be able to read a menu by the time we are done. Now we are leaving the big city life and heading to a tiny town called Hallstatt in the Salzkammergut (Salt Mining) region of Austria.
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Hallstatt</title>
    <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2012 06:47:08 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1340966828</guid>
    <description>Hallstatt,  Austria</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-06-29 06:47:08</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-29 10:47:08</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Hallstatt</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Hallstatt<br/>Hallstatt,  Austria </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Hallstatt,  Austria</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
The village of Hallstatt, Austria is the epitome of a postcard town. Sandwiched between mountains and the lake, the town is situated on one narrow street, with a few cobbled lanes branching off. Every view is either a breathtaking mountain vista or picturesque little Austrian houses perched on the mountainside. All the houses have immaculate flower window boxes and tiny flower gardens. Amanda described Hallstatt as "the cutest town in the world," and she is probably right. Our last two stops were cities with well over a million people, but Hallstatt has less than a thousand permanent residents. I'm sure that number is much higher in the summer because of all the tourists. Hallstatt has no hotels, only gasthofs (guesthouses), so it seems to be more if a day trip for the tour buses. From 10am to 6pm the town swells with the elderly and Chinese/Japanese tourists (the two main groups who like to travel in packs and use tour bus groups). The Chinese love Hallstatt so much, they have cloned it! Click here for more info. We thought Hallstatt was small enough to not have too many tourists, but the crowds were pretty easy to avoid. We spent the middle of the day exploring the outskirts and surrounding attractions. Around dinner time, we felt like we had Hallstatt to ourselves. The two semifinal matches of the European Cup soccer tournament took place on the two nights we were there. There are only a couple of bars in town, and we watched the matches with locals. The second match was Germany vs Italy, and it became quickly apparent that Austrians were pulling for Italy. We watched the second half back at the campground with several Germans. I struck up a conversation with an older German couple, and even though they spoke very little English and I speak even less German, we had a pretty good conversation. They are from somewhere near Munich, and I told them I was from America &#246;sten and s&#252;den (east and south). They have some some sort of connection to Atlanta (family maybe?). I told them we were pulling for Deutschland because we are going to be in Munich on July 1st, the day of the final. They also asked if my father or grandfather was Deutsch, because of my hair and eyes. I told them it went further back than that, but I do have German heritage. The most notable activity we did in Hallstatt was a tour of the salt mines. Hallstatt's salt mine is way up the mountain above the city. We had to ride a funicular to get there. The mountains around Salzburg (Literally Salt City), are full of salt deposits. The salt mine at Hallstatt has been active for over 4000 years. The Hallstatt salt trade was so important in the prehistoric times that a period of the Bronze Age is called the Hallstatt era. The town and mine have been declared a UNESCO World Heritage Site because of the history associated with Hallstatt. The tour even included wooden slides that the miners used to get to certain areas quicker (video at the bottom). One problem we had in Hallstatt and several other places, is the difficulty getting tap water with a meal. We are on a tight budget, so we can't afford to be spending &#8364;3 every meal on a Coke or bottle of mineral water. Most places will begrudgingly bring you a tiny glass of water if you ask, but some just refuse. I learned that leitungswasser means tap water to try and better get my point across, but it is still difficult. We always carry bottles if water around, so it's not a big deal to get no drink with a meal. We are not sure how anyone in Europe stays hydrated if they never drink water. Hallstatt was a great start to our break from cities. As we go further south, the less major cities, and the more small towns we are visiting. Munich, Florence, and Rome are the only big cities left on the itinerary. Salzburg, next up, is fairly large at 150k, but still a small and manageable city.
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Salzburg</title>
    <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1341154811</guid>
    <description>Salzburg,  Austria</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-07-01 00:00:00</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-07-01 04:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Salzburg</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Salzburg<br/>Salzburg,  Austria </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Salzburg,  Austria</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
Salzburg is the city of Mozart and The Sound of Music. While the thought of Salzburg evokes romantic notions of classical music and stunning landscapes, the city was disappointing. It is ironic that the city so heavily promotes itself as the birthplace of Mozart, but Mozart himself couldn't wait to leave and moved to Vienna at 24. The cities other biggest draw, The Sound of Music tours, leave the city and venture out into the countryside. The best way we could think to describe the city is that someone came through and painted all the buildings various shades of beige and paved the city with asphalt and gravel. Half the stores in town sell the same brand of Mozart souvenirs, and the streets are lined with vendors selling other Austrian knickknacks. There are a couple nice parks, but the historic center has no green space. It didn't help that the temperature was around 35 degrees celsius during the day. I'm not sure exactly what that is in Fahrenheit, but it's in the 90s. Our campground was fairly nice and even had a pool! It was very nice to come back after sweating all day in town and jump in the pool. But the pool, like many other places in town closed at really odd times. It was open from 9am until noon, then closed until 2, then reopened until 7pm. I know they have siestas in Spain and Italy, but it seems a little ridiculous for a pool with no lifeguard in Austria. Salzburg definitely had the highest concentration of grocery stores of any city we've been to. That's good, because we make a lot of picnic meals from the grocery store, but it was difficult make it to a grocery store when it was open. All the SPARs (the chain of grocery stores that were everywhere) closed at 6pm on Saturday and were not open at all on Sunday. Most of the restaurants in Salzburg are either Italian or Greek, so we were surprised to come across a decent looking beer garden. We were beered out, but we did get a couple sausages that turned out to be the worst things we have eaten in a long time. There is a SPAR at the mall across from the train station, and the whole mall closed at 6. We got lucky and decided to check the SPAR in the train station (yes, there are literally two full size grocery stores of the same chain across the street from each other), and it stayed open til 11 and was open on Sundays! We were so tired of schnitzel and frankfurters that we bought a bunch of fruit and vegetables for salads and snacks. Normally I wait to write about our leaving train ride for the next cities entry, but this ride was so fitting of our time in Salzburg that it deserves to be here. We got up early to check out and catch the train to Munich. Ironically, we got on a RailJet, which is Austria's fastest and nicest train, but it was the most annoying hour and a half of the trip. Soon after we sat down, a family from somewhere in the Middle East sat down a couple rows in front of us. I'm not sure if they even knew how many kids they had, but I counted 7. They all appeared to be spaced roughly 9 months apart. The kids looked like the ones in the commercials trying to get you to send 15&#162; a day to feed and clothe them. The father showed his ticket to Augsburg to most everyone around him, and everyone told him, "No this train only goes to Munich." He was told this repeatedly in German and English, but still decided to stay on the wrong train. I guess no one really corrected him, because they were at least going the right direction. The conductor checking tickets explained to him how to make the Augsburg connection, but I don't think he understood any of it. I wouldn't be surprised if they are in Zurich right now. The kids did not stop screaming/singing/making weird noises the whole ride. The mother made them all white bread and hotdog sandwiches, which they proceeded to get more on the floor than eat. The family was sharing a 2liter bottle of Coke. One of the kids apparently didn't like his sip because he spit it into the aisle of the train. He made it ok though by rubbing it into the carpet with his foot. After they were done with the Coke bottle, they felt that the appropriate method of disposal was to throw it on the floor. The one thing that really took the cake though, the mother changed the youngest babies' diaper in the train seat, without putting a blanket or towel or anything down. There were baby changing tables in the WC 15 feet away! After the conductor announced that we would be in Munich in 5 minutes, the mother found it a good time to walk aisle of the train while breast feeding the youngest baby. Well I guess nobody bats a thousand, and we certainly missed on Salzburg. The city probably would've been more enjoyable if weren't overshadowed by our recent memories of the baroque grandeur of Vienna and the spectacular mountains of Hallstatt. Oh well, we're looking forward to Munich!
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Food</title>
    <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1341167592</guid>
    <description>Salzburg,  Austria</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-07-01 00:00:00</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-07-01 04:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Food</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>draft</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Food<br/>Salzburg,  Austria </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Salzburg,  Austria</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
H
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Munich</title>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1341473688</guid>
    <description>Munich,  Germany</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-07-05 00:00:00</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-07-05 04:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Munich</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Munich<br/>Munich,  Germany </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Munich,  Germany</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
Munich is the capital of the German state of Bavaria and what the average American thinks of when he or she imagines Germany. There are really tons of beer gardens, and I'm sure Oktoberfest is wild. Our stay in Munich was somewhat uneventful from a sightseeing standpoint, but was still very interesting. We ended up staying in Munich for four full days, double what we had planned, because Amanda had some sort of nasty stomach virus. As a nurse, she has a very strong immune system, so when she does catch something, it is usually pretty serious. Day 1: We arrived early from the Salzburg train and made it out to our hostel/campground, aptly named The Tent. This was the most interesting place we have stayed yet, and definitely my favorite. I have never been to a hippie commune, but this is what I would imagine it to be like (check out The Tent's Website), complete with impromptu folk concerts around the bonfire. It is basically a large compound with 4 large tents with bunks and floorspace that slept hundreds of people, green space for tents, a cafeteria, reception, bathrooms/kitchen/laundry, tons of picnic tables, ping pong tables, a volleyball area and a basketball court. To further supported the hippie description, The Tent is very into recycling. Any glass bottle drinks you buy there, you pay an extra 1&#8364; deposit that you get back when you return the bottle. The beer and soda companies then come and pick up the bottles to reuse. It is a very direct way of recycling. Unlike the hostels and campgrounds we have been to so far, The Tent seemed well represented by many nationalities and languages. The crowd was mostly young to middle age, but there were a few older people there too. The Tent served very inexpensive food, and I think there were many people there who didn't leave the compound, and had no intention of leaving anytime soon. After we set up our tent, we ventured to the nearby Augustiner Beer Garden, the oldest in Munich. Later we watched Spain and Italy in the final of the Euros with a huge crowd at The Tent. I've don't know what we're going to do at night now that soccer is over. Even Amanda has been getting into the matches; it's easy when the crowd around us is so animated. Congratulations to Spain for winning its third consecutive major international tournament. As a former goalkeeper, I have the upmost respect for Iker Casillas, who has not allowed a goal in an international elimination match since 2004, a total of over 900 minutes. I know Kristin was excited, by her Facebook post of simply "&#161;Espa&#241;a!". Day 2: We first went out to Allianz Arena, Bayern M&#251;nchen's new stadium. It was here that Amanda started not feeling well, and we went back to The Tent. After she rested, she felt better and we worked some on our itinerary and budget. We have been monitoring the weather over Switzerland for a few days, and it looked bad enough that we considered rerouting and coming back up through Italy in a week or so. But any solution we came up with was too time consuming and expensive. It is nice that we are flexible enough to even consider it though. The weather was supposed to be bad in Munich too, but we only got rain in the evenings. We are hoping the same holds true for Switzerland. Day 3: Amanda woke up feeling terrible. She threw up a couple times in the morning. We had to scrap our plans of doing anything that day so she could rest. In the afternoon, she felt well enough to go with me to the grocery store and pharmacy, but she ended up throwing up on the sidewalk as soon as we got off the tram. We got some drugs for her and some food, then went back to The Tent for her to rest more. While she was sleeping, I ended up playing basketball with a Libyan-Canadian guy who was part of the freedom fighters who ousted Gaddafi, and he told me how much better life is for the people there. He now works as a car importer, and he was bringing BMWs back to Libya. Later, I talked to a German guy about the differences between the way American and German sports leagues work. His English wasn't the best, but I talked slowly and didn't use big words, and we had a good conversation. At the tent, we ran into the Australian guy we met on the night train from Amsterdam to Copenhagen a couple weeks earlier. Amazingly, not only did he see us again, but in Prague, he ran into the Swiss couple from our same cabin. Earlier in the day, the Swiss couple had run into the Australian lady. So all six members of our cabin bumped into another member down the road. He had been to Berlin, Prague and Krakow before ending up in Munich. He said Krakow was really nice except for the heat. Of all the travelers we have talked to, Krakow has been the most recommended destination. That's interesting because Krakow was not on our radar at all during our planning. Day 4: Amanda woke up feeling much better. She still wasn't 100%, but we did make it into the city for some sightseeing. We walked around the Olympic Park area first. It's hard to believe the complex is over 40 years old; it was a revolutionary building system at the time, and still looks modern. We ate lunch and walked through the English Gardens, famous for its nude sunbathers and surfers. We did see some nude sunbathers, but it was mostly old men with too little shame. It is odd to think of surfers in Munich, but there is a rapid on the river in the park that forms a surfable wave. We sat for a while and watched them take turns; it was one of the coolest things we have seen yet (Video coming when I can get it uploaded). We saw the main square, Marienplatz, and I had a way too big beer at the place-you-just-kinda-have-to-go-to when you're in Munich, the Hofbrauhaus. It is a giant beer hall that doesn't offer it's two primary beers in anything smaller than 1 liter steins. I feel like we basically lived at the Tent for 4 days, but that's okay. As the cheapest and most interesting place we stayed, it helped our budgets and we certainly weren't bored. We didn't get to see Dachau, the first concentration camp, but I feel like we experienced the city. Hopefully the weather holds out in Switzerland, and Amanda can shake off the last bit of this bug on our long train ride day.
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Switzerland</title>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1341597708</guid>
    <description>Lauterbrunnen,  Switzerland</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-07-06 00:00:00</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-07-06 04:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Switzerland</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Switzerland<br/>Lauterbrunnen,  Switzerland </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Lauterbrunnen,  Switzerland</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
Switzerland was the one country we were the most excited about on this trip, and we can say that it certainly did not disappoint. Whether we were up at top of Alps or down in valleys, the views were breathtaking. We are already planning out trip back! We left Munich very early and barely caught the 7:17 train to Zurich. Our original plan was to go all the way to Lauterbrunnen on the train that day, stopping in Zurich, Lucerne and Interlaken. We knew we wanted to stop and at least see a little bit of each of those cities. We ended up booking a hostel for one night in Interlaken, because the forecast was calling for heavy rain in Lauterbrunnen, and we are getting tired of setting up and taking down our tent in the rain. Lauterbrunnen is only about 20 minutes from Interlaken, but the valleys in the Alps each have their own "microclimates." It can be pouring rain in Lauterbrunnen but perfectly sunny in Grindelwald, one valley over. We first stopped in Zurich, but for only less than an hour. We grabbed lunch in the station, and got our first shock of how steep the Swiss prices were going to be. After we scraped most of the stick of butter that was on each sandwich, we walked a little ways down the Bahnhofstrasse, Zurich's main shopping street, and then back. It is nice how compact and organized Swiss cities are. We tried to stop for a just a couple hours in Brussels and basically got lost and didn't see much. Lucerne was the same way as Zurich. We walked from the train station through the Kapellbr&#252;cke, a famous covered wooden bridge with paintings dating back to the 1300s, on to the old town and circled back. We only spent about an hour and a half in Lucerne, but we saw the heart of the city. Interlaken is quite a different place. The hotels are still there from its days as popular resort town for the wealthy in the early part of the last century, but now it is more of a base for extreme sports. At one point we saw 10 paragliders airborne over the city at the same time. Every shop you walk in offers to book your extreme sports adventures, from bungee jumping to skydiving out of a helicopter, for a hefty fee. I would have been more likely to go paragliding than Amanda, but there was no way she would let me go. She doesn't even like the cable car rides. Our "hostel" was the only place we could find with openings in all of Interlaken, but it was basically a grouping of large tents. Our tent had six bunks, a plywood floor and a light. We made a good decision because it did rain pretty heavily that night and most of the whole next day. Surprisingly, a month of mostly sleeping on the ground hasn't really bothered us, but packing up and carrying around a wet tent has not been fun. We made it to our campground in Lauterbrunnen pretty early in the day, and set our tent up before it started raining again. For reference, Lauterbrunnen is a small town at the entrance of Lauterbrunnen Valley, a spectacularly huge U-shaped valley with literally hundreds of waterfalls cascading down. The largest is Trummelbach Falls, but it isn't visible from the valley; it is inside the walls of the mountain. We could have seen it for 22 CHF (Swiss Francs - note: 100 CHF is 108 USD, so pretty similar in value), but we decided to skip it. The second largest falls was right beside our campground, the wispy Staubbach Falls. The water becomes mist because it takes so long to fall to the valley floor. It does somehow manage to collect at the bottom, but depending on the wind, the waterfall can be blown fifty to sixty feet in either direction. Above Lauterbrunnen, only accessible by special trains and cable cars are two ski towns, M&#252;rren and Wengen, and the little village of Gimmelwald. Towering above the valley are the spectacular snowy peaks of the Eiger, the M&#246;nch, and the Jungfrau (the Ogre, the Monk, and the Young Girl). There are hundreds of other smaller peaks, but the three are what the area is known for. Lauterbrunnen valley is in the center of Switzerland, and Switzerland is in the middle of the Alps. It really feels like we were in the absolute heart of the Alps. It is a truly spectacular place. We probably took as many pictures in one day here as the rest of the trip combined. We would marvel at every view, only for it to be topped by rounding the next corner. Our campground was very large and very nice. They had a restaurant and a store that wasn't much smaller than the average European grocery store. The only minus is that they charged outrageous fees for wifi and Internet access, 5 CHF for 30 minutes of use. We soon found a cafe called Airtime in town, less than 10 min walk, that gave out their wifi password if you bought anything. Not only was it a cafe, but an adventure booking center and laundromat. Swiss francs are the most interesting currency we have encountered yet. The bills look like they were designed by someone on some powerful hallucinogenics and the coins feel like the quality of Chuck-E-Cheese tokens. In the US, the highest value coin we regularly use is 25&#162;, and Euros go up to 2&#8364; coins. The Swiss use coins all the way up to 5 CHF. It is a weird feeling to pay for an entire meal with a few coins. We soon discovered that our campground had bungalows that are a popular spot for tour buses. Not the elderly or Asian buses like we have become used to, but a young party bus company called Contiki (they say on the buses that they are the most popular tour for 18-35 year olds. There were between 2 and 4 buses there each night. The crowds seemed to be mostly Australian, but there were some Americans too. The Contiki'ers we talked to generally assumed we were on one of the buses, and seemed amazed when they found out we had planned our own trip and were doing our own thing. We were concerned, because when we first got to Lauterbrunnen, it was raining and the visibility was very low. We found out that one of the Contiki groups had taken the train up to the Jungfraujoch, a train station 3000 meters up between the Jungfrau and the M&#246;nch. At the top they were only greeted by thick fog and sub freezing temperatures. There budget must have been a lot bigger than ours, because they didn't seem to care that they had spent 150 CHF to be in a cloud. One guy's quote was "Well the pictures inside the building looked nice.". We were concerned we would have bad weather for whatever we decided to do the next day. We started planning for good and bad weather while watching the Wimbledon Semifinals, that saw Roger Federer and Andy Murray advance to the finals. We got into a conversation with an older English couple about how the English support the Scottish athletics ( Andy Murray is Scottish and the first Brit make it to the finals in 75 years), but the Scots hope the English always lose. The husband then went on to tell me how great American Music is; he is a big fan of Irving Berlin, and he doesn't like the newfangled stuff like The Beatles. After his little rant, he told us that they had been coming to Lauterbrunnen for 50 years, and we soon figured out that he was a walking encyclopedia of the region. He explained the best trains and cable cars to get to the most spectacular views in the area. There are dozens of cable car and train lines in the Lauterbrunnen and Grindelwald valleys. They are run by a private company and not covered on our Eurail passes, but we did get a 25% discount. We started on a pretty tight budget and the unexpected costs are really starting to add up. We woke up the next morning very excited to see blue skies. We started off by taking a cable car and train up to M&#252;rren. As soon as we left the valley floor, we were greeted by spectacular views of the three peaks. We had decided that we would take the cable car up to the Schilthorn (the other major excursion besides the Jungfraujoch - but for closer to half the price) if it was a perfect day. Since it was about as good of weather as we could ask for, we took the cable car up from M&#252;rren to the Schilthorn, about 3000 meters or 10,000 feet above sea level. As soon as we stepped out of the cable car, it felt like we were in a different world. They say on a clear day you can see as far as the Black Forest in Germany, but we had some clouds. I'm not sure how far we could see, but it seemed incredibly far. The Schilthorn also gives amazing views of the Jungfrau, M&#246;nch, Eiger and hundreds of other surrounding peaks. The Schilthorn is capped by the famous revolving restaurant Piz Gloria. We were there early enough to enjoy the breakfast buffet, while rotating around the 360 degree panorama views. It was interesting because only the outer seating area revolved, not the center or the windows. It was difficult to find our seats after we went to the buffet, and if you sat anything on the window ledge it would stay behind while you rotated onwards. Someone was even writing notes and passing the butter this way. The Piz Gloria has no shame in admitting it was a James Bond filming location. They sell many 007 souvenirs, there are 007 decals on the windows, and the waiters even have 007 embroidered on their shirts. What they don't tell you is that the movie was In Her Majesty's Secret Service, the one James Bond movie starring George Lazenby. Have you ever heard of George Lazenby? Of course not! George Lazenby's grand kids don't even know he was James Bond. Excited tourists go to the small theater downstairs that shows clips from the movie, expecting to see Sean Connery or Roger Moore, only to walk out saying, "Who was that guy?". There are a few intense hiking trails down from the summit, and we walked a little ways down each. The view from here was so spectacular, it would almost be worth the cost of the whole trip just to be on the Schilthorn. On our way back to the cable car, we saw a paraglider putting on his gear. We, along with some others, helped hold his parachute up while he was preparing to take off. I don't know how long it took him to travel the odd 2000 or so meters down to the valley floor, but I'm pretty sure we passed him as we went down in the cable car 15 minutes later. Once we were back in M&#252;rren, we set out to hike the "North Face Trail" to Gimmelwald. I'm not sure why it's called that, as it's not on the north face of anything, but it was a great hike nonetheless. We spent the first portion hiking through a dense pine forest, but the majority of the trail was through cow pastures. Switzerland is known for its dairy products, and these types of fields are everywhere, even up on the side of a mountain. One portion we had difficulty even getting through because of all the cows in the way. Amanda even got shocked by an electric fence. All along the trail were little cottages, farmhouses I guess, that seemed like you could rent. One had a group of college looking guys sitting around drinking beer. I'm sure it would be a very interesting experience to stay at one of these, the only way in and out is a 30 min to 1 hr walk to town, totally surrounded by the Alps. We even saw a couple of little guesthouse/restaurants along the path. I have no idea how a place with no roads runs a restaurant, but they do. About half way to Gimmelwald, we decided to climb a "small" mountain named Bryndli that over looks the village and valley below. I guess our eyes were bigger than our legs, because we only made it up 3/4 of the way up. We thought we were almost at the summit, but when we rounded what we thought was the top, we saw there was still a good bit to go. We didn't pack enough food and water, so we headed back down, and started the hour descent to Gimmelwald. It's tough to walk a steep descent for two hours, and we could really feel it in our legs by the time we got down. Along the way we stumbled upon a really great waterfall (it's still amazing how many waterfalls are in the valley). After we ate, we had planned on continuing the walk down to the valley floor to Stechelberg, but we opted for the cable car instead. Then we walked along the river part of the way back to Lauterbrunnen, and caught the bus back for the rest. We were very sore the next day and contemplated spending it in Lauterbrunnen, but the weather forecast was poor, and it even rained on us as we packed up (what a surprise). So we decided to head on to Zermatt. The ticket checkers on the trains generally barely glance at our railpasses, and we have never had to show our passports to actually prove they are ours, but we had problems on the Interlaken to Spiez train. At only 20min, it was the shortest train ride yet, but the ticket lady looked at our railpasses for awhile, then said "One minute" and took them to the front of the train. The train was in the act of stopping as she walked away and we needed to get off. We ran her down and told her we needed to transfer there. She mumbled something about how our passes weren't complete, and told us to go to the ticket office. We said ok, and proceeded to get on our next train. Nobody has questioned the passes since. We knew that the trains in Lauterbrunnen were private, and our passes didn't cover them, but nowhere did we see that our passes didn't cover the train from Visp to Zermatt. On the train, the ticket checker informed us that we had to pay 51 CHF each to get to Zermatt. You think there would be someone to check tickets before you get on the train, but it is easy to get on a train you're not supposed to. The $100 we had to pay was really the straw that broke our budget's back. Little (or big) unexpected charges have really added up (more on this later). Zermatt is a really interesting town. My Mom remembers it as a quaint little mountain town, but in the past 30 years, it has become a major ski resort. In the summer, the main street is still bustling with tourists, hikers, and climbers, but the outskirts feel like a ghost town. There are no cars here, only funny miniaturized electric trucks that mainly serve as taxis and hotel shuttles. The town's main attraction is the amazing Matterhorn mountain. Unlike Lauterbrunnen, which is surrounded by dozens of huge mountains, Zermatt is surrounded by hills (that would be mountains in SC) and the Matterhorn towers above it all. It's craggy, sheer faces are really a sight to behold. For those Bachelor fans who are reading, we have been to the final two locations of the last season, Interlaken and Zermatt. Coincidently we also left London and Prague the day after each of those episodes of the current season of The Bachelorette aired. With our downtime, we have been keeping up with our reality TV the best we can with spotty Internet and the ABC app on our phones. I think Emily is going to pick Sean, but Amanda thinks Jef. We haven't seen the latest episode yet though, so don't ruin it for us. The population of Zermatt seemed about 10% permanent locals, 10% hardcore hikers and climbers, 80% Asian tourists, and then us. The Asian groups were very entertaining because they were totally decked out in very nice hiking gear, but we never saw any of them out on the trails. They were using their trekking poles just to walk out of the sidewalk. One odd thing we have noticed everywhere, but especially in Zermatt, is the startling number of people walking around with camcorders. They walk the streets with the camera rolling and film every little bit of everything. They only see Europe through the little screen on their video camera. One guy was just standing and filming the Matterhorn, like something amazing was going to happen, but the mountain just sat there, looking the same as it has for thousands of years. I do love that my phone can take good quality video, and I have filmed quite a few things, but it's always short videos of things a photo doesn't really do justice. While we were in Zermatt, we had to make the tough decision of scheduling home an earlier flight. We are about 70% of the way through, but we have already burned through 100% of what we budgeted for the trip. We could afford to finish, but we don't want to be totally broke when we come home. Both our parents have offered to help us, but it's not totally about the money. It is more a combination of money, costs, weather, and other general annoyances. The most annoying thing is that it is so expensive to do anything, no matter who's money it is. That's not to say we haven't enjoyed it, because the trip has been great, but it's just little things start to add up, and we are ready to come home. We have tried so hard to save money, but it is impossible. It's no fun to skip eating at a restaurant and buying food at a grocery store, only to realize that we spent 80% of the restaurant cost. Even if we had triple the budget, I couldn't justify spending money on what some of this stuff costs. In Zermatt, albeit an expensive resort town, an 8oz Coke at a restaurant, with no refills, costs over $4.50. Not everywhere is that bad, but it is still expensive. One meal we bought and cooked in Lauterbrunnen cost of over $20 just for spaghetti, one small chicken breast, vegetables, and tomato sauce. We have been gone long enough that the way we do things has started to feel like a way of life and less like a vacation. It's fine for a while, but it is starting to wear on us. The camping and moving around has been totally fine. We aren't tired of sleeping in the tent, but the weather has dampened on our spirits somewhat. At the start of the trip, we didn't see the sun until the second day in Copenhagen; that's 6 countries we travelled through under clouds. While walking around the city in cloudy, cold and occasionally rainy weather isn't too bad, packing a wet tent and never being able to dry clothes has not been fun. Every European we have talked to has remarked about how exceptionally wet and cool this summer has been. We are finishing with a blitz of the two places we wanted to see most in Italy, Cinque Terre and Rome. Our next trip to Italy trip will have a bigger budget to see the places we are missing and eat more of the food. We are cutting out 12 days, which is probably about the average Italian vacation. We are already planning our trip back, but it won't be in July. We can already tell that Italy is very hot and very crowded. Look out for Cinque Terre and Rome posts soon!
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>

 

  <item>
    <title>Italy</title>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator><![CDATA[ johnandamanda ]]></dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">1_1342007580</guid>
    <description>Rome, Italy</description>

    <wp:post_date>2012-07-11 00:00:00</wp:post_date>
    <wp:post_date_gmt>2012-07-11 04:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
    <wp:post_name>Italy</wp:post_name>
    <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
    <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>

    <content:encoded>
<![CDATA[

<!-- ENTRY HEADER STARTS -->
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="10" align="right" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="center" padding: 20px;>
      <div style="width:50%; margin:auto; padding:10px; border:2px solid #eeeeee; text-align:center;"> Italy<br/>Rome, Italy </div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
<b>Rome, Italy</b>
<br/>
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY HEADER ENDS -->

<!-- ENTRY BODY -->
Our Italian trip basically consisted of the Cinque Terre and Rome. The Cinque Terre (Five Lands) consists of five tiny towns that cling to the rocky cliffs of the Italian riviera: Monterosso has the only beach, is the biggest and has most of the hotels, Vernazza offers postcard views of its picturesque harbor, Corniglia is the smallest and way up on a hilltop, Manarola is picturesque and has a small harbor with plenty of swimmers and rocks to leap off, and Riomaggiore is the furthest south and seems the most precariously hung from the cliffs. All the towns are connected by a 9km hiking trail that ranges from two hours to 20 minutes between the towns. When we decided to fly out earlier, we allocated our last few days as follows: 1 day to get from Switzerland to the Cinque Terre, 1 day in the Cinque Terre, 1/2 a day to get to Rome, a quick stop in Pisa, the rest of the day to see what we can in Rome, then fly out the next morning. I know it sounds crazy to go to Rome for less than 24 hours, but we reasoned that when we come back to Italy we will definitely will see more of Rome, but we can do enough of the Cinque Terre and Pisa and not feel like we have to come back to those. It was a real shock to come from Switzerland to Italy. The countries border but couldn't be more different. When we came out of the tunnel into Italy, everything just looked so &#8230; Italian. There's not really any other way to put it. Even in the far north part, the buildings were roofed with red tile, the paint was peeling from the stucco, and the landscape just looked different. Amanda later remarked that everywhere else we've been that reality looks better than the pictures, but in Italy, the pictures look better. Though the most significant change for us was the train system. Swiss trains (Really all the countries so far, but especially Switzerland, Germany, and Austria) are modern, clean, efficient, and most importantly, timed perfectly. Our train from Brig stopped in Domodossola and we had to change from to a regional train to continue on to Milan. This train was fine, but there were little things noticeable: the train seemed older, the bathrooms weren't as clean, the doors often jam, etc. When we got to Milan is when we started having problems though. We arrived at s smaller outlying station and needed to get to Milan Central to continue onto Genoa and the Cinque Terre. The boards that displayed departures didn't list anything, but the paper timetables listed a train that runs to the central station every 30 minutes. Seeing one in a few minutes, we had to run to furthest platform, only to see no train. We still have no idea if it left early or never came, but the platform sign displayed the train we needed, even as a different train came and left the platform. We decided to go talk to the information desk, where we had to wait 30 minutes in line. The man at the desk told us very rudely to take the metro and not worry about that train. When we got down to the metro area, we attempted to buy metro tickets from the automated machine. The machine had the nerve to tell us that it did not accept coins, and when we tried to use a 20&#8364; bill, it said "Insert Less Money." We were finally able to get tickets from one of the magazine and tobacco kiosks. At the Central Station we found out that the big departures screen listed the trains leaving, but not what platform they depart from. Everyone congregates around the screen and when the platform is finally displayed, they rush off to try and board the train in time. The Italian train boards even have a "delay" column, which we didn't see in any other country. We were trying to get on the 18:05 train, but soon realized that the same train that was supposed to leave at 16:05 still hadn't left, and was listed with a 100' delay. We confirmed it was going where we wanted, and got on. The train ended up leaving at 18:00, 115' late. We never saw the 18:05 train. Ironically, all the other countries' trains are air conditioned, but the hottest country, Italy, has had the little to no air conditioning on the trains. You basically sit and sweat. When we finally got to Levanto, a larger town just north of the Cinque Terre, and the location of our campsite, we were relieved, but it was about 9:30 at night and we couldn't find anything to eat, even after getting directions from the guy at campground. He first told us there was one twenty meters on the right, which was just a dried up river bed. When we came back and told him we couldn't find anything, he told us to try 1 kilometer to the left. We could have walked into town, but it was late and we weren't exactly sure where anything was. That night was the low point of our food experiences on the trip; we remembered we had a couple cans of chicken noodle soup left from Munich when Amanda was sick, so we sat on a blanket on the ground and ate it cold. We were laughing because it was so pitiful. We got up early the next morning and took the train to Monterosso, the northernmost of the five towns. By train, it takes only about 5 minutes between the towns because there are tunnels, but the hike is about two hours because you have to go up and over the mountains. Monterosso seemed empty at 8:30, but the beach was full when we came back later in the day. We decided to tackle the most daunting hike, the two hour stretch from Monterosso to Vernazza. The first 30 minutes was straight up, then an hour of relatively flat, then another half hour of downhill. The whole Cinque Terre area is a national park, so the trails were pretty popular and well maintained. Several people we saw didn't look at all prepared for the heat and the difficulty of the hike; some were even wearing flip flops. The descent down to Vernazza gave us several vantage points that are obviously where the post card pictures are taken. Vernazza, like all the other towns except Monterosso, is car free. Narrow streets wind between the buildings going up the hillside. They are considered streets there, but are about the width of the sidewalk. There wouldn't be any point in even owning a bicycle. There were a good bit of people sunbathing and swimming from the rocks around the harbor. From Vernazza, we took the 5 minute train ride to Corniglia. The train station is about a 10 minute walk to the bottom of the hill the town is on, and then there are roughly 400 steps up to the town. There is even a sign at the bottom encouraging visitors to make the trek up: "You will be amazed by the historical center of Corniglia." We were not amazed. Corniglia was the smallest, least interesting, and hardest to get to of the five towns. Our next stop was Manarola, probably our favorite of the group. The small rocky harbor had spots for sunbathers and jumping rocks for daredevils, and there were plenty of cafes lining the streets. It was a short and easy walk to great postcard vantage point of the town. Manarola and Riomaggiore are connected with a easy paved and flat walk called the Via Dell'Amore (Path of Love). Riomaggiore is the furthest south of the five and our last stopping point. It was set up similarly to Manarola, but not quite as interesting. After taking the train back to our base of Levanto, we decided to pick a town to go back to for dinner (we had more money for the eating experiences after we decided to come home earlier). It's only a five to fifteen minute train ride to any of the towns, but in Italy no distance is too short to be exceptionally complicated by train. The bigger stations at least have boards and announcements that tell you what train is leaving from the platform, but at the smaller stations, it is a **** shoot. There is no indication on the train or platform where the train is going. The only thing to do is to find the train we wanted on the paper timetable, stand at the platform indicated and hope the train was there at roughly the right time. This did not work in Levanto. We were at the right platform, but a different train rolled up the correct time for the one we were expecting (we should have known - the trains never show up at the correct time in Italy). So we got on, but were surprised when it starting blowing past all the stops we needed. The first station it did stop was La Spezia, the major town of the region and the next stop after the southernmost town of the Cinque Terre, Riomaggiore. There were at least 8 of us in La Spezia of who got on the train thinking it was stopping in the Cinque Terre. We ended up talking to a mother and daughter from Dallas a good bit, and they recommended a restaurant to us in Monterosso. We didn't have any definite dinner plans, so we decided to try it. After waiting on another late train to take us back, we got off and walked to the restaurant. The food was great, but we realized that we were in a bind while we were eating. Several days earlier, our trip debit account was almost empty so we transferred money from our main bank account. Everything would have been fine, but the transfer was taking way longer than expected. Our backup cards were credit cards, but we didn't have pin numbers for them, so we couldn't use the ATMs (Bancomat is the European name). We wanted to catch the early train to Pisa and then to Rome, which was left before our campground opened. We needed to check out, and to make that train we had to check out that night. I remembered that the campground only accepted cash, and we had no cash and no way of getting any. We had some backup USD that we could exchange at a bank in the morning, but that wouldn't get us on the early train out. About that time, the mother and daughter from the train who suggested the restaurant walked in, said hi to us and found a seat. I felt bad for asking, but since we were in a bind, I asked them if they minded exchanging 50 Euros for $80 USD. They were nice and helped us out, but we took basically all of their cash. We gave them a great rate though: 50 Euros are worth about $65 USD. We knew our campground closed at 11pm, and after waiting on a late train back to Levanto, we barely made it back before closing. But it turned out that the guy at the desk was only a night watchman and couldn't check us out; the office actually closed at 9pm. So we were forced to wait until the office opened back up at 8:15 the next morning, and we got on a 9am train to Pisa. Though if we hadn't had the USD to exchange, we might still be in Levanto waiting on that bank transfer (it finally did go through after we got home - big help there). It amazed us how little prepared some of the travelers we ran across were. That night, after we talked to the night watchman, a couple college age American guys strolled into the campground at about 11pm. They asked the night watchman if they could camp there, and he told them sure, they could set up and pay in the morning. They then revealed that they didn't have a tent and asked if they could rent one. He looked at them like they were crazy and told them no (some of the campgrounds do rent tents, but I don't know why they would wander through a town just hoping to find one in the middle of the night). He then informed them that all the hotels in town were probably full and they would most likely have to try somewhere else. The day before, when we first got off the train in Levanto about 9pm and were looking for our campground, we ran across another backpacker. We asked him if he knew where the campground was. He told us he didn't even know if there were any campgrounds in town, but he wanted to stay in one. Apparently he just randomly got of the train hoping to find a campground. I was aware of three, but only had a mental map of where they were. He asked for the most beautiful one, so I directed him toward the one closest to the beach. Traveling in Europe is stressful enough when you have an idea of what you're doing, we have no idea how these people managed to stay sane (or where they slept!) just wandering around. We enjoyed the Cinque Terre, but were glad to be moving on to Rome. We had to change trains in Pisa, so we decided to see the tower. It is about a 10min bus ride from the train station, and when we got off the bus we entered the most touristy area of the whole trip. The tower area is totally lined with souvenir shops, and there are hordes of people holding their arms out to "prop" up the tower. Some people were even sitting on each others' shoulders trying to make a cliche shot unique. It was a giant mess, so we took the cliche pictures just to prove that we had been and got out of there. The bus to take us back to the train station was late, and we only made our train by a few seconds (there wasn't another for two hours). The train to Rome was roughly four hours long with no air conditioning. We were hot and surrounded by loud Italian kids playing Uno. We booked a hostel for our last European night at a place near the Rome Termini station so we could save some time by not walking so much. We didn't get to Rome until around 5pm and our flight was at 11:52 the next morning. Rome wasn't built in a day, and it certainly can't be seen in half of one. We managed to see the outside of the Colosseum, the outside of the Roman Forum, the outside of Circus Maximus, and the one fountain closest to the train station. We took some pictures to prove we were actually there, but we will have to come back to really see the city sometime. We wanted to see the Vatican as well, but it was so hot and the subways so crowded, we decided to wait til next time (sorry Nancy). The Rome Airport ran about as smoothly as the trains. For some odd reason they decided that all American (and Israeli for some reason) flights should leave from Terminal 5. They don't tell you that T5 isn't connected to the airport at all, but a 10 minute shuttle ride from the main terminals. At T5, we checked our bags and went through security, but then were bused right back to the main terminal. Amanda bought a really fitting shirt at the Rome hostel, the back of it says something like this: Heaven is where The police are British The cooks Spanish The mechanics German The lovers Italian and it is all organized by the Swiss Hell is where The cooks are British The mechanics Spanish The police German The lovers Swiss and it is all organized by the Italians The whole airport was a mess, but we finally did make it home. 5 weeks is a long time to live the gypsy lifestyle that we did, but we really got used to it. It was bittersweet because we had such a great time and met so many interesting people, but we were ready to come home. We missed out on some of Italy that we had planned, but that's just a good reason to plan another trip, but it won't be in the middle of the summer! By the end, we could navigate train stations and public transportation with the best of them. Even Amanda, who had first left the EST zone only two years ago, was moving through Europe with ease (she has common sense, a lot of travelers we met didn't). I have really enjoyed writing the blog, and I appreciate all the feedback and comments I have received. It seems like everyone has really liked reading it. I looked back on some of the first posts, and it's really interesting how much longer and more detailed I got. I think there is a direct correlation between the train distance to the next city and how long the blog post is though! I calculated that I wrote roughly 15,000 words, the vast majority using one finger on my iPhone (Travel Pod really needs to let their app turn sideways - at least then I could use two fingers). I will miss writing the blog, but now we go back to our lives and they're not as interesting! Thanks for reading, John and Amanda
<br/>
<!-- ENTRY BODY ENDS -->    
<br/>

]]>
    </content:encoded>
  </item>



</channel>
</rss>